<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-28T20:53:48+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Portfolio of Ritten Roothaert</title><subtitle>The portfolio of Ritten (H.M.) Roothaert. This webpage showcases my projects, which are mostly related to AI, XAI, hybrid AI and  ML. The preferred programming language used is Python, although some projects are written java and scala. For questions, please get in touch  with me though email or my socials.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bachelors Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/03/05/Wildfire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bachelors Project" /><published>2020-03-05T14:48:14+01:00</published><updated>2020-03-05T14:48:14+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/03/05/Wildfire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/03/05/Wildfire.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/RUG_logo.svg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;Pumpkin flower&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Logo of the university of Groningen
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my bachelors project, I used reinforcement learning to train an
agent in controlling forest fires. In order to do so, me and three other
 students from the University of Groningen build a forest fire simulation 
and implemented several reinforcement learning techniques. My main 
contributions were the agent implementations and the connectionist monte-
Carlo algorithm inplementation. The final grade awarded to this project 
was a 7.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source code can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ritten11/Wildfire-Control&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Due to the lack of 
running instructions and proper documentation, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fse.studenttheses.ub.rug.nl/21637/&quot;&gt;thesis&lt;/a&gt; might 
be more informative&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Logo of the university of Groningen For my bachelors project, I used reinforcement learning to train an agent in controlling forest fires. In order to do so, me and three other students from the University of Groningen build a forest fire simulation and implemented several reinforcement learning techniques. My main contributions were the agent implementations and the connectionist monte- Carlo algorithm inplementation. The final grade awarded to this project was a 7.5.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ProSeed Seed Selector</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2019/01/30/ProSeed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ProSeed Seed Selector" /><published>2019-01-30T14:34:10+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-30T14:34:10+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2019/01/30/ProSeed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2019/01/30/ProSeed.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/pumpkin_flower.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;Pumpkin flower&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Image of a pumpkin flower
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my first projects was the ProSeed Seed Selector, which is a tool 
which allows the user to optimize the seed selection for creating hybrid 
pumpkin seeds. The application uses knowledge provided by organic seeds 
breeder “De Bolster”, to determine the phenotype of the child plant after 
breeding with two parents plants. The current version is a demo version 
based on mock data, but has been validated by an expert breeder. The 
program could therefore be used as a useful tool for any pumpkin breeder 
once real data is fed into the application. The final project was awarded 
with an 8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ritten11/Pumpkin-Drools-Public&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, along with running 
instructions. The source code has not been made available at the request
of the experts involved in making this application.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Image of a pumpkin flower One of my first projects was the ProSeed Seed Selector, which is a tool which allows the user to optimize the seed selection for creating hybrid pumpkin seeds. The application uses knowledge provided by organic seeds breeder “De Bolster”, to determine the phenotype of the child plant after breeding with two parents plants. The current version is a demo version based on mock data, but has been validated by an expert breeder. The program could therefore be used as a useful tool for any pumpkin breeder once real data is fed into the application. The final project was awarded with an 8</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First update</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2018/01/01/Welcome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First update" /><published>2018-01-01T13:34:10+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T13:34:10+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2018/01/01/Welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2018/01/01/Welcome.html">&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post provides the starting point of my portfolio. Project are added in chronological order, ranging from school projects, to theses and competition submissions. Each project has a small explainatory introduction explaining the premis and the used techiques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a full overview, see &lt;a href=&quot;/../&quot;&gt;the overview page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">This post provides the starting point of my portfolio. Project are added in chronological order, ranging from school projects, to theses and competition submissions. Each project has a small explainatory introduction explaining the premis and the used techiques.</summary></entry></feed>