<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-30T16:44:25+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Portfolio of Ritten Roothaert</title><subtitle>The portfolio of Ritten (H.M.) Roothaert. This webpage showcases my projects, which are mostly related to AI, XAI, hybrid AI and  ML. The preferred programming language used is Python, although some projects are written java and scala. For questions, please get in touch  with me though email or my socials.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Master’s Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2022/11/25/CO2DataAssimilation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Master’s Project" /><published>2022-11-25T14:48:14+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-25T14:48:14+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2022/11/25/CO2DataAssimilation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2022/11/25/CO2DataAssimilation.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/RUG_logo.svg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;University of Groningen logo&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Logo of the university of Groningen
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The environment is changing due to anthropogenic carbon emissions, and so is the carbon cycle regulating the exchange of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (i.e. fluxes) between the Earth’s surface and the atmosphere. Measuring these changes is difficult, as it would require enormously dense observation networks to capture the strongly heterogeneous underlying flux-landscape. Through a combination of carbon exchange (CE) models and data assimilation (DA), the CarbonTracker data assimilation shell (CTDAS) generates a flux-landscape estimate which optimally matches the available observations. The current implementation of this DA approach is static; flux-landscape estimates produced in the past are not used for estimating new flux-landscapes. However, preliminary research has shown that seasonal, currently unused, patterns are present within the estimates of the DA approach. We propose three different methods for utilizing these patterns: a simple monthly mean model, a seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average (SARIMA) model, and a seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average with exogenous factors (SARIMAX) model. Preliminary results strongly indicate that the monthly mean model provides a substantial improvement over the current DA implementation once incorporated within CTDAS. In contrast, the SARIMA and SARIMAX models struggle to capture the non-stationary seasonal patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full thesis can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/downloads/mAI_2022_RoothaertHM.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the source code is found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ritten11/MasterProject&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Logo of the university of Groningen The environment is changing due to anthropogenic carbon emissions, and so is the carbon cycle regulating the exchange of CO2 (i.e. fluxes) between the Earth’s surface and the atmosphere. Measuring these changes is difficult, as it would require enormously dense observation networks to capture the strongly heterogeneous underlying flux-landscape. Through a combination of carbon exchange (CE) models and data assimilation (DA), the CarbonTracker data assimilation shell (CTDAS) generates a flux-landscape estimate which optimally matches the available observations. The current implementation of this DA approach is static; flux-landscape estimates produced in the past are not used for estimating new flux-landscapes. However, preliminary research has shown that seasonal, currently unused, patterns are present within the estimates of the DA approach. We propose three different methods for utilizing these patterns: a simple monthly mean model, a seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average (SARIMA) model, and a seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average with exogenous factors (SARIMAX) model. Preliminary results strongly indicate that the monthly mean model provides a substantial improvement over the current DA implementation once incorporated within CTDAS. In contrast, the SARIMA and SARIMAX models struggle to capture the non-stationary seasonal patterns.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">iGEM Groningen 2021: Bye-Monia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2021/10/27/ByeMonia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="iGEM Groningen 2021: Bye-Monia" /><published>2021-10-27T15:34:10+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-27T15:34:10+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2021/10/27/ByeMonia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2021/10/27/ByeMonia.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;https://static.igem.org/mediawiki/2021/1/17/T--Groningen--LogoByeMonia.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;Bye-Monia logo&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Logo of the iGEM Groningen 2021 team: Bye-Monia
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, I was a part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://2021.igem.org/Team:Groningen&quot;&gt;iGEM team of Groningen&lt;/a&gt;. iGEM is a global 
competition focusing on finding solutions to local societal problems 
using synthetic microbiology. For our iGEM project, our team decided 
to contribute to mitigating the Dutch nitrogen crisis. This crisis is a 
result of the Netherlands emitting too much nitrogen containing 
compounds into the air. Once in the air, these compounds are deposited 
into nature reserves where they cause eutrophication and acidification, 
resulting in a loss of biodiversity in these areas. Our project was 
eventually nominated for 5 awards, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://2021.igem.org/Team:Groningen/Model&quot;&gt;best model&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://video.igem.org/w/5om7x44MZ3weFFBqABZ3DH&quot;&gt;best 
project presentation&lt;/a&gt;. We reached top 10 within 
the overgraduate category and, as icing on top of the cake, we won the 
best environmental project in the overgraduate category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main emitters of nitrogen containing compounds is the Dutch 
agricultural industry, with the cattle industry in particular emitting 
almost half of the total ammonia emissions within the Netherlands.
We decided to modify a Saccharomyces spp. such that it is able to 
excrete alpha-amylase. This enzyme hydrolyses glycosidic bonds in 
complex sugars. We reasoned that by adding this enzyme to the feed of 
cattle, the animal would be better able to digest polysaccharides, 
increasing the digestive efficiency and cause it to excrete less ammonia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to maximize the activity of the alpha-amylase excreted by our 
alpha-amylase producing Saccharomyces spp. (from now on also referred to 
as our ‘device’), we looked at the effect of 10 different promoters, 4 
secretion signals, 4 alpha-amylase genes and 4 chassis, creating a 
combinatorial library with 640 different combinations of parts. We set 
out to test 64 of these combinations and use machine learning (ML) in 
order to make predictions on the untested combinations. The tool used 
for this is called the automated recommendation tool (ART). The 
predictions made by this tool were both exploratory, giving an 
indication on which combinations should be tested in order to reduce the 
uncertainty within the ML model, and exploitative, giving an indication 
on which combinations are expected to yield the highest activity based 
on the training data. Designing and analysing the ML approach to our 
project was one of my main contributions to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we managed to produce usable activity measures for 47 
devices. After training the ART, it became apparent that using one 
specific secretion signal and one alpha-amylase gene would most likely 
result in the highest activity. Furthermore, one promoter also appeared 
to be outcompeting the others. No clear preference for chassis was 
observed, and thus we decided to use the chassis which showed the 
highest growth rate. Unfortunately, we did not have enough time to test 
the final device and verify the predictions made by the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides wet and dry lab work, our team also put substantial efforts in 
outreach, both in the form of &lt;a href=&quot;https://2021.igem.org/Team:Groningen/Gold_Human_Practices&quot;&gt;human practice (HP)&lt;/a&gt; and in the form of 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://2021.igem.org/Team:Groningen/Communication&quot;&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;. With our human practice work, reached out to stakeholders and 
used their advice in order to make adjustments to our product such that 
their needs are taken into account. My role in this part of the project 
was supporting Milou, as she was our HP manager. This support consisted 
of brainstorming with her, filling in various HP tools, reaching out to 
stakeholders and conducting stakeholder interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the education part of our project, our education team created 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://2021.igem.org/Team:Groningen/education/comics_en&quot;&gt;several comics&lt;/a&gt; aimed at teaching elementary school children (aged 6 to 
12) basic concepts within synthetic biology, along with a lesson plan on 
how to use these comics in a classroom setting. Additionally, several 
webpages were created where the actual science behind each of the comics 
is explained. These webpages targeted an older audience, mainly 
focussing on the parents of the elementary school children. Besides 
translating some materials and brainstorming on how to set up the 
webpages, my contribution to this part of the project was limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final contribution to the project was being in charge of the 
finances. I made the budget, kept track of our income and expenses, 
directed sponsoring requests to Chienes from the GBB, and explained to 
the other team members how they can declare the expenses they made for 
the project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Logo of the iGEM Groningen 2021 team: Bye-Monia In 2021, I was a part of the iGEM team of Groningen. iGEM is a global competition focusing on finding solutions to local societal problems using synthetic microbiology. For our iGEM project, our team decided to contribute to mitigating the Dutch nitrogen crisis. This crisis is a result of the Netherlands emitting too much nitrogen containing compounds into the air. Once in the air, these compounds are deposited into nature reserves where they cause eutrophication and acidification, resulting in a loss of biodiversity in these areas. Our project was eventually nominated for 5 awards, including best model and best project presentation. We reached top 10 within the overgraduate category and, as icing on top of the cake, we won the best environmental project in the overgraduate category.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modeling ‘The Resistance’ using epistemic logic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2021/06/21/LAMAS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling ‘The Resistance’ using epistemic logic" /><published>2021-06-21T15:34:10+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T15:34:10+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2021/06/21/LAMAS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2021/06/21/LAMAS.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/resistance.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;Boxart of 'The Resistance&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Boxart of 'The Resistance'
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the course ‘Logica Aspects of Multi-agent Systems (LAMaS)’, me and two
fellow students modelled ‘The Resistance’ using epistemic logic. The 
Resistance is a multiplayer deductive reasoning role-playing game. Using 
a multi-agent based approach, we tested how the usage of higher-order 
knowledge could increase the win-rate of the agents. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://ritten11.github.io/LAMAS2021/&quot;&gt;full report&lt;/a&gt; 
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ritten11/LAMAS2021&quot;&gt;implementation&lt;/a&gt; are available online. The final grade 
for the project was a 9.
&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Boxart of 'The Resistance' For the course ‘Logica Aspects of Multi-agent Systems (LAMaS)’, me and two fellow students modelled ‘The Resistance’ using epistemic logic. The Resistance is a multiplayer deductive reasoning role-playing game. Using a multi-agent based approach, we tested how the usage of higher-order knowledge could increase the win-rate of the agents. The full report and implementation are available online. The final grade for the project was a 9.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modeling the spread of SARS-CoV-2 within dutch public trains</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/10/04/DoMAS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling the spread of SARS-CoV-2 within dutch public trains" /><published>2020-10-04T15:34:10+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T15:34:10+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/10/04/DoMAS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/10/04/DoMAS.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Coronavirus_H.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;Reder of the SARS-CoV-2 virus&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Digital render of SARS-CoV-2. &lt;p class=&quot;source-link&quot;&gt;Source: https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/covid-19&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot happened in the year 2020. A massive increase in hospital admissions due to the SARS-CoV-2 virus pandamic put a substantial strain on the dutch healthcare system, resulting in unpresidented measures being taken to slow the spreading of the virus. One of those measures was enforced social distancing within the dutch public transport, including the train network. Me and three other students at the University of Groningen deceded to test the effectiveness of this social distancing method, and wanted to see wether we could improve upon the current strategy by implementing different seating arrangements and boarding strategies. We did so using a multi-agent system approach, in which we modelled the train route from The Hage central station to Groningen central station. The code of the simulation can be found on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Daankrol/D27-DMAS-Corona-spread-train&quot;&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt;, and the results are given in &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/downloads/DMAS_Alpha_version.pdf&quot;&gt;our report&lt;/a&gt;. The final grade was an 8.
&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Digital render of SARS-CoV-2. Source: https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/covid-19 A lot happened in the year 2020. A massive increase in hospital admissions due to the SARS-CoV-2 virus pandamic put a substantial strain on the dutch healthcare system, resulting in unpresidented measures being taken to slow the spreading of the virus. One of those measures was enforced social distancing within the dutch public transport, including the train network. Me and three other students at the University of Groningen deceded to test the effectiveness of this social distancing method, and wanted to see wether we could improve upon the current strategy by implementing different seating arrangements and boarding strategies. We did so using a multi-agent system approach, in which we modelled the train route from The Hage central station to Groningen central station. The code of the simulation can be found on our github repository, and the results are given in our report. The final grade was an 8.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bachelor’s Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/03/05/Wildfire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bachelor’s Project" /><published>2020-03-05T14:48:14+01:00</published><updated>2020-03-05T14:48:14+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/03/05/Wildfire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2020/03/05/Wildfire.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/RUG_logo.svg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;University of Groningen logo&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Logo of the university of Groningen
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my bachelors project, I used reinforcement learning to train an
agent in controlling forest fires. In order to do so, me and three other
 students from the University of Groningen build a forest fire simulation 
and implemented several reinforcement learning techniques. My main 
contributions were the agent implementations and the connectionist monte-
Carlo algorithm inplementation. The final grade awarded to this project 
was a 7.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source code can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ritten11/Wildfire-Control&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Due to the lack of 
running instructions and proper documentation, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fse.studenttheses.ub.rug.nl/21637/&quot;&gt;thesis&lt;/a&gt; might 
be more informative&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Logo of the university of Groningen For my bachelors project, I used reinforcement learning to train an agent in controlling forest fires. In order to do so, me and three other students from the University of Groningen build a forest fire simulation and implemented several reinforcement learning techniques. My main contributions were the agent implementations and the connectionist monte- Carlo algorithm inplementation. The final grade awarded to this project was a 7.5.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ProSeed Seed Selector</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2019/01/30/ProSeed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ProSeed Seed Selector" /><published>2019-01-30T14:34:10+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-30T14:34:10+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2019/01/30/ProSeed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2019/01/30/ProSeed.html">&lt;!--&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/profile_picture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
   &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/pumpkin_flower.jpg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 200px;&quot; alt=&quot;Pumpkin flower&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; 
							font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
		Image of a pumpkin flower
		&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my first projects was the ProSeed Seed Selector, which is a tool 
which allows the user to optimize the seed selection for creating hybrid 
pumpkin seeds. The application uses knowledge provided by organic seeds 
breeder “De Bolster”, to determine the phenotype of the child plant after 
breeding with two parents plants. The current version is a demo version 
based on mock data, but has been validated by an expert breeder. The 
program could therefore be used as a useful tool for any pumpkin breeder 
once real data is fed into the application. The final project was awarded 
with an 8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ritten11/Pumpkin-Drools-Public&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, along with running 
instructions. The source code has not been made available at the request
of the experts involved in making this application.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Image of a pumpkin flower One of my first projects was the ProSeed Seed Selector, which is a tool which allows the user to optimize the seed selection for creating hybrid pumpkin seeds. The application uses knowledge provided by organic seeds breeder “De Bolster”, to determine the phenotype of the child plant after breeding with two parents plants. The current version is a demo version based on mock data, but has been validated by an expert breeder. The program could therefore be used as a useful tool for any pumpkin breeder once real data is fed into the application. The final project was awarded with an 8</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First update</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2018/01/01/Welcome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First update" /><published>2018-01-01T13:34:10+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T13:34:10+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2018/01/01/Welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/update/2018/01/01/Welcome.html">&lt;!-- excerpt-start --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post provides the starting point of my portfolio. Project are added in chronological order, ranging from school projects, to theses and competition submissions. Each project has a small explainatory introduction explaining the premis and the used techiques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt-end --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a full overview, see &lt;a href=&quot;/../&quot;&gt;the overview page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritten Roothaert</name></author><category term="portfolio" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">This post provides the starting point of my portfolio. Project are added in chronological order, ranging from school projects, to theses and competition submissions. Each project has a small explainatory introduction explaining the premis and the used techiques.</summary></entry></feed>